Where did I grow up? In Jerusalem.
I'm a resolute Jerusalemite.
HUDA AL-IMAM FOUNDER & DIRECTOR CENTER
FOR JERUSALEM STUDIES, JERUSALEM UNIVERSITY
I am a resident of Ramallah,
my family is originally from a village called Al-Haditheh
near Ledd and Jaffa.
The village has been destroyed.
LEILA ATSHAN
CONSULTANT PSYCHOTHERAPIST
I did not leave!
They forced us to leave.
We were forced out in 1948.
I was 4 years old at the time.
MEMBER, PALESTINE NATIONAL COUNCIL MEMBER, POLITICAL
BUREAU, POPULAR FRONT FOR THE LIBERATION OF PALESTINE
MARY NAZZAL BATAYNEH
BARRISTER AT LAW/ ACTIVIST
We left over several phases.
We went back and forth a number of times.
MALAK AL-HUSSEINI ABDELRAHIM FOUNDING MEMBER, ASSOCIATION
FOR THE DEVELOPMENT OF PALESTINIAN CAMPS (INAASH)
Maybe if I were in Meiroun now,
I might not necessarily be living in the village,
I might be living in Haifa, for example,
AMAL ZIAD KAAWASH
ARTIST & SINGER/ SONGWRITER
Every single day, as I return home
I slow the car down
and look out at Jerusalem
I take a deep breath
especially under the snow in winter
when the weather is good
I think to myself “This is why I am here”.
DINA NASSER
REGISTERED NURSE & HEALTH ADVISOR
My father's family left in 1948
and fled to Nabatiyyeh
then my mother and father got married
and went to live in Tal al-Zaatar Camp.
From Tal al-Zaatar
we came to Mar Elias Camp
and we are still here
in Mar Elias Camp.
NAZMIYEH SALEM
EMBROIDERER
We were always moving from place to place
it was something of a nomadic life
every few years we'd move to a different place.
Then, my parents immigrated to Canada
and my sons studied there,
so, it's really a geographic mosaic.
SALMA AL-YASSIR DIRECTOR GENERAL
INSTITUTE FOR PALESTINE STUDIES
I was born in Jerusalem,
we then lived in Amman for a while,
then we moved to Beirut,
then I went to Tunis,
then I went to the US.
Finally, I returned to Ramallah.
RAEDA TAHA WRITER & ACTOR
DIRECTOR KHALIL SAKAKINI FOUNDATION
In 1981, I went to Palestine on a visit,
to study Palestinian architecture.
I thought I would be there for only six months.
I fell in love with Palestine
and I fell in love with a man in Palestine
and as a result I decided to take up
a teaching post at Birzeit University.
SUAD AL-AMIRY FOUNDER &
DIRECTOR, RIWAQ NOVELIST
I truly regret it
because we could have
continued to go until 1967.
We had 10 years,
but... I don't know.
SIMA TUQAN GHANDOUR FOUNDING MEMBER, ASSOCIATION
FOR THE DEVELOPMENT OF PALESTINIAN CAMPS (INAASH)
With every stitch,
she hides a story,
a thought,
a sigh.
Inside each of us,
inside the map of Palestine,
our stories were like threads
that separate then come together,
recounted and then hidden,
when faced with the "knot" of occupation.
A knot that rearranged all the threads,
scattering them in all directions.
A single life was now assigned two threads:
one thread that is real,
another that could have been.
The stories transcended Palestine.
Their threads dispersed, seeking refuge or exile.
Those women who remained in their homeland
were accused of non-existence.
It was said to them: You are not here.
They responded:
We are not a lie inside a plot,
we are here.
And wherever we are,
we narrate stories in detail,
embroidering them on the face of our earth.
Some are privileged,
others bearing life in a camp.
First, second, third generation.
Accents and cities,
classes and cultures differ.
They are very different from one another
but all meet at one turning point
where all threads meet:
the before and the after,
before 1948, and after it.
At that turning point,
Palestine was transformed.
It became a homeland the size of a planet.
Both my mother and father are Lebanese
entirely Lebanese.
They are originally from Tyre.
But my father went to Palestine,
at that time there were no borders
and people would go there in search of work.
50, my father went to Palestine to work.
He returned, married my mother
and they went back to live in Haifa.
When we were forced out
they returned to Tyre.
My mother took us
to her uncle's house in the city of Tyre.
It is quite close to Haifa,
only about an hour and a half away.
When we arrived at my mother's uncle's house,
there was an entrance lined with orange trees.
The oranges were still on the trees.
As we approached to pick oranges,
my mother slapped our wrists like this.
"These are not your oranges
your oranges are in Haifa.
These are not yours.”
We are not supposed to touch what is not ours.
Ever since that moment,
I have hated oranges.
Every time I see oranges,
I remember that moment
that “These are not yours”
that "Your oranges are in Palestine, in Haifa.”
My father was granted a permit
to meet his mother at the Mandelbaum Gate.
This was in 1964.
He went there,
of course, he needed a permit to come to Jordan,
papers from the International Red Cross and so on.
He spent 3 days at the Mandelbaum Gate
without seeing his mother
because the Israelis had not notified
his mother that her son was coming.
My father came back,
a little while later
he suffered a stroke and was paralyzed.
He never got to see his mother.
Whenever I see anything Palestinian,
whether a painting or an olive branch,
I long to return to Palestine.
I'm not the only one,
all of us refugees
want to return to Palestine.
I became involved in military
operations, from a young age.
It made me feel that Palestine was closer.
The more politically involved I became,
the closer I felt to Palestine.
I don't mean geographical closeness
but emotionally and in my being.
I was elated.
I remember the first three nights in the camp,
I didn't sleep,
I didn't sleep a wink.
I told them I was ready to stay on guard duty
all the time, every single day,
without sleep.
When I first held a rifle,
I felt like...
I was not married at the time,
but I used to feel that the rifle
was like a baby
being cradled in its mother's arms
That's how I felt.
I would hold it protectively.
I felt that the rifle
would take me to Palestine.
It would take us all back.
Of course, I had been educated about this.
We were, educated about Why.we.'
were engaged in armed struggle.
All the readings on popular revolutions,
especially the Algerian women's struggle,
the 'Jamilat' who had
performed all those heroic feats.
The 'Jamilat' who had
I used to wonder,
why aren't we like them?
Why don't we do what they have done?
These real-life experiences
gave us more hope and dreams
that it can become a reality.
Algeria was under French
colonization for 130 years,
colonization, torture of women,
assassinatlons etc...
Yet, they were liberated.
That means that we too can liberate Palestine.
These are the kinds of
comparisons we would make.
I would imagine how I was
going to arm we in Haifa,
how I would pick oranges
and eat them with their peel
and find dates.
Isn't it funny? You would
be working on something big
but it's those small dreams...
no one would smack me on the wrists and say"These aren't your oranges!'"
When I got married
I wore the traditional robe.
I didn't have a wedding
but I wore the 'thobe'.
For me it was
a kind of attachment,
)
not only in the political sense, .- -*
but because this is
a symboll of who we are.
In 1975,
we were attend in a conference
when a group of girls wearing
Palestinian 'thobes' passed by.
I asked “Where are these girls from?”
They turned out to be Israelis.
We went berserk!
"How dare they wear our 'thobe'?!”
It does not belong to them.
So we took a decision that the entire
delegation would wear 'thobes' and put on 'kuffiyas',
People started coming up to us
and asking "Are they in your delegation?”' -
We would answer '“No! Those are
the people who stole our country
and stole our heritage.'
That's it.
They are the thieves,
we are the real people of the land,
we are the real bearers of the 'thobes'.
In my case, I could not
afford to buy a 'thobe'.
Personally, I didn't have
the financial means to buy a 'thobe'.
When I went to Kuwait
as part of an official delegation
after my the military operation,
a woman came up to me and said
"I want to give you a 'thobe' as a gift",
she was an old woman
she had embroidered it herself.
You see, In the past each girl
used to embroider her own 'thobes'
and keep them safe in her chest.
Those who had
embroidered several 'thobes'..
Each 'thobe' requires a
lot of work, around six months.
This woman gave me the first
'thobe' she had ever embroidered.
According to her, this was
the most beautiful 'thobe' she owned.
I took it and I still have it until now.
Another woman gave me a 'thobe' as a gift.
The 'King Thobe' is the wedding 'thobe',
it is usually embroidered with a golden thread.
She had prepared it for her son's bride
but her son was martyred.
So she gave it to me.
She said to me "No one would
take better care of it than you.”
This was in Lebanon,
where the martyr's mother lived.
The bride-to-be hadn't
had a chance to wear it.
I took it and I told her
“I will not wear it
until I return to Palestine.
It is a very precious gift
that you are giving me.”
It was made by a mother
for her son who was martyred.
I will never forget this.
Imagine...even as I am
speaking now, I remember
how much pain this mother is in
over the loss of her son
who was about to get married.
She had prepared his bride's 'thobe',
she couldn't find a way
she wanted to give it to someone
she didn't keep it for herself.
For her to give it to me..
This was the most valuable gift
I have ever received.. until this day.
Unfortunately, during the 1982 war, the Israeli
invasion of Lebanon, this 'thobe' was destroyed.
I'm from Jerusalem.
We left in several phases.
We went back and forth a number of times.
The 1936 Revolt had started
and my father was wanted
by the British army.
That's why we had to leave Jerusalem.
My father had to flee
and he took the familiy.
We came to Lebanon for a short while
but then the French came to Lebanon,
we had to flee from them
so, we went to Baghdad.
We stayed there for a few years
but the British were
searching for my father again
and he fled to Iran.
In Iran, they captured him.
They captured him and took him to Rhodesia,
it's now called Zimbabwe,
they kept him in jail for five years.
Meanwhile, we went back to Jerusalem
and I went to the Quaker school in Ramallah.
Then, I came here to Lebanon
to attend the Junior College.
We did go back
because they processed the Family
Reunification documents for us
it's for Palestinian families.
The Israelis gave all my sisters Jerusalem IDs
but they refused to give me a Jerusalem ID
I was given a Jericho ID.
I asked, "Why have you given me a Jericho ID?
I was born in the German Hospital in Jerusalem!"
They said, No, we've given you enough Jerusalem IDs.
I have maintained my connection,
we need to go once every 3 years
we need to go there.
To the West Bank,
I can go whenever I want.
But the problem is, what do I have in Jericho?
Our house in Jericho is abandoned,
my sisters all go to Jerusalem,
we had many houses,
but they're all gone now
we have to stay in a hotel.
I used to sneak in from Jericho
they would smuggle me into Jerusalem
straight to the hotel.
Sometimes I'd go out,
but when I do go out
I feel very sorry for myself.
I think to myself, Curse them,
this is my country
yet I'm scurrying along like a mouse
frightened of being seen
I scurry along near the walls and corners;
This is my country, I was born here
my parents died here and are buried here
and I'm made to feel like a prisoner.
Do you remember your house?
Our house?
Yes, yes, it's with the Jewish settlers now.
It's in the Messrarah area.
I’ll tell you the story with my mother,
the first time we went,
it was with my mother
we were all together, all the sisters,
my mother insisted she wanted to go see her house
it was her father's house.
It was a very large house,
one of the oldest in Jerusalem.
They were the first family to leave the Old City
and move to the new city.
They just crossed the road
and built a house there.
He built a huge spacious house.
When the problems started, we left
and the Jewish settlers confiscated it
all of it.
It had close to 40 rooms that they had rented out.
50, my mother took us with her to Messrarah,
we protested that we couldn't face it
but she insisted,
"Even if you can't I want to see it...
We took a taxi and drove there
we stopped in front of the house
my mother got down with her cane,
she must have been 75 or 80 years old
there she stood with her cane.
We refused to get out of the car
and sat there crying and frightened.
She got out with her cane,
climbed up the front stairs,
and knocked on the door with her cane
like so...
tick ... tick ... tick
The Jewish settler opened the door,
the lady renting the house,
my mother said “I want to see my house!”
The woman answered “No madam)
this is our house, we have bought rt”.
She answered "I've never sold it,
my father built it”
she kept saying "My father built this house, my father,
I want to see every room”.
Embroidery is important for me because
I have been surrounded by it my entire life.
I've been seeing embroidery my whole life,
ever since we were in Jerusalem.
When I first opened my eyes
our Nanny was wearing the 'thobe'
I would see how it was embroidered all over.
When we went to the village, to Jericho,
\
we would see the women at the water spring
all wearing beautiful dresses.
However, it had never occurred
to us to learn from them,
or to copy their designs.
We just knew that it was
something very beautiful.
Now our country is gone,
we don't have our country any more,
but we have embroidery
and this, no one can take away from you.
When you're embroidering a piece, it is yours.
It gives me a lot of pride »
when I see how beautifully it turns out.
I used to do European style cross stitching.
I would be happy with it,
but it wasn't personal to me.
Now, when we produce a beautiful piece,
it's my national embroidery.
It has become a nationalist issue for me.
It's more than embroidery,
it's about national belonging.
All our work at INAASH since the
very beginning up until now
Is based on designs and
motifs from old thobes'
going back to around 1848
this period of 100 years.
All this embroidery is derived from that period.
The 12 windows project began
about 25 or 30 years ago.
When we still had hope of establishing our own State.
We wanted to create something
that we can present to our State
we thought of a producing a large mural
depicting the different regions of Palestine
which would be our gift,
whether to our Parliament,
or national museum,
to be our gift to Palestine.
Recently, we decided to revive this project.
We began to think "Why not
work on different regions of Palestine"?
We did our initial research and found
that there are roughly 12 embroidery regions.
50, according to those 12 regions,
we named the project '12 Windows'
Palestine, from its North to its South.
In all cases, it's too late
I am now ...
I won't tell you how old I am,
but I'm very old.
Would you like to know?
I turned 85 yesterday!
Yesterday I became 85 years old,
what would I go do now?
To start with, I cannot cross the bridge,
I cannot ride 4 buses
and carry my suitcase on and off.
And I have nowhere to go.
In Jericho, there are no hotels.
I am not allowed to go to Jerusalem.
If they know that I go,
they'll kick me out on the spot.
I'm listed as being from the West Bank,
but the only thing I know is Jerusalem,
That's where I grew up,
I want to go to Jerusalem.
——
I was born In Jafa
but we lived in Jerusalem
We left Jerusalem in 1948
and came directly to Lebanon, straight here
I remained a few month without school
then | went to Alexandria
where | spent a year at school in Alexandria
I finished school
and returned to Lebanon.
I'm one of the very early ones.
Primarily, I have only
worked in embroidery at INAASH,
and this is what I still do,
this is my job.
And that's it.
This is my place at INAASH.
One day I was at a meeting
of the Friends of Jerusalem,
Huguette Caland happened to be passing by
She is the daughter of Beshara Al-Khoury,
the former President of Lebanon.
She stopped to talk to me,
she said "SIMA,
Chermine GHANDOUR Hneineh and |
are thinking of doing something for Palestine”.
This was after 1967,
you must remember.
She said something
that I will never forget,
something very beautiful.
Every time I tell this story I start to cry...
"One day, we will have Palestine back
and everything Palestinian
must return with it
heritage, food, whatever.
We prepare it here,
and when we get Palestine back,
all this will return with it.”
Our needlework started with 'tricot'
but, that is not Palestinian work
it has nothing to do with Palestine.
So we began to search
for mothers, older women
for those who had pieces
at home, who had 'thobes'
and we started with what we had.
We decided to start by making cushions.
And it took off.
We then produced a generation
that knows how to embroider,
and another generation that embroiders,
we provide them with the materials,
and the design, the main lines,
and they put it together
according to their tastes.
They remain at home,
they embroider at home,
they have an income,
and at the same time
they look after their children
and perform their household duties.
Let me tell you what
embroidery signifies to me.
When I was a little girl in Jerusalem
I remember making myself a skirt.
A seamstress came and
sewed a black skirt for me
and I embroidered it all around the hem.
At that time we used to embroider
camels, and Bedouins with canes,
all of these went on my skirt.
I embroidered all of them
and I used to wear It.
I used to love embroidery.
At the nuns' school,
they teach you embroidery,
they teach you sewing,
they teach you everything.
I also remember the village women
who used to come to Jerusalem.
Some selling eggs
door to door, carrying baskets
some who came to do our laundry,
we didn’t have washing machines then.
They were all around us,
Jerusalem was surrounded by villages.
To me, embroidery was linked to villages.
In Jerusalem, we lived in
an area that the British had zoned off.
You could only enter and leave with a pass.
It is al-Baqa'a al-Fawqa and Qatamoun.
My grandfather's house was in Jaffa
and I was always going back
and forth to my grandparents'.
I lived at my grandparents'
as much as I did with my mother and father.
I was very close to my
grandmother and grandfather.
For me, Jaffa is part of me.
As soon as school closed for holidays,
my mother would immediately pack
my bag and put me on the bus,
the public busses,
she’d ship me off to Jaffa.
I'd go by bus
and they would meet me
at the other end.
I'd spent the entire summer
I'd stay in Jaffa.
Jaffa, Jaffa is part of me
Oh! I loved Jaffa.
What happened to it?
You can't imagine what has happened to it.
He brought me photos,
I almost fainted!
The house is on Salameh Street
it's in an area between Tel Aviv and Jaffa.
Now, it's between
Tel Aviv and Jaffa,
it used to be Jaffa.
It also had an orange orchard
half the orchard had also
been destroyed earlier
but it was a large house.
When my mother was first
married, they lived there.
The house is there,
but it's In a terrible state.
Of course, there's no more orchard,
or garden or anything,
they've even pulled down the balcony.
What can I tell you, it's horrible.
When he showed it to me
I said, "Why would you show it to me?
I don't want to see.
Let me stay with my souvenirs".
It's horrible.
Like everyone else we thought
it would be a matter of 15 days and we would return.
15 days...
Go for 15 days then you can return.
My father went to Nablus
and we went
via Amman
because Haifa was over,
it had been taken over,
via Amman to Beirut.
To Broumana not Beirut.
Broumana, up there!
It was a horrible journey.
There was me, my mother,
my uncle was driving,
and one of my brothers was with us
the youngest, Usama, was with us.
Sami, funnily enough, stayed
behind at St. George's School.
He stayed on behind us.
Later, they brought him out.
We went directly to Broumana.
And I remember
my mother never stopped crying.
From the beginning of
our journey to the very end.
And that was it.
Then from Broumana
we moved to Beirut.
And that was it.
The 15 days became
how long? 65 years?
That's it.
My father is from Jaffa
and my mother is from the district of Haifa.
My father's parents were displaced to Lebanon,
and my mother's family went to Jordan,
so I was born in Amman,
because my mother wanted\
to give birth near her family!
but at the time,
we were living in Lebanon.
After Lebanon, my father went
to work in Saudi Arabia,
I returned here to Beirut,
and stayed in a hoarding school for a while.
During the war (in Lebanon)
we moved around,
we went to Jordan,
returned to Lebanon,
then we went to the UK.
I studied in the UK
and graduated from there.
I returned to Lebanon for a short time
then I got married and moved to Cyprus
where I stayed for around 14 years.
After that, my parents emigrated to Canada,
my children studied there,
so, it's really a mosaic of geographical locations.
This piece of embroidery reminds me of Palestine.
I love blue because I love the sea.
I am a daughter of Jaffa.
Jaffa and the sea are in my blood,
the memory of the sea of Jaffa
through my father
we grew up with stories...
For me, it's linked to my memory
as if it's part of me.
It's very significant to me,
maybe it's in the genes,
I tell you my grandfather was a seaman.
He worked in the sea.
They owned barges to transport oranges.
As you know, Jaffa is all orchards
there was trade,
and the transport of goods, especially oranges.
They lost all of it.
Now I've heard wild tales of how
they used to put gold coins in tins
and bury them under the ground.
Now, just how true that is, I don't know
but these are the tales they tell,
that they left behind them many things
they left properties,
they left money...
They left thinking that they would be returning,
like everyone else.
But they remained here.
As far as I know, the family
did not all leave at once.
My grandmother stayed behind for a while,
and my grandfather took the children,
then my uncle went back for my grandmother.
From what I've heard,
my grandmother was a tough Jaffa woman.
She had her standing
it wasn't easy for them to convince her to leave.
It was actually she,
who insisted that I my father get an education
my father and his younger siblings.
My grandfather had wanted them
to work with him in the sea,
but my grandmother put her foot down
insisting that he gets an education.
I myself grew up with Jaffa,
I grew up with the idea of Jaffa.
It was as if we were there.
From the stories,
what the house was like,
how my grandfather would come
into the house with muddied shoes,
and how my grandmother
would chastise him
"You soiled my floors",
etc. etc.
How there was a basin near the entrance,
she was obsessive about cleanliness.
50, we were able to imagine
what the house was like.
They were 7 brothers.
As youngsters, they used to
like to run away from school.
They would skip school
and go swimming in the sea.
My grandmother, who was known
to be a very tough woman..
They would wait for the school day to end,
then come home pretending they'd been at school.
She'd ask where they'd been
and they'd answer 'At school”.
If she doubted them,
she would hold them one by one
and she would lick them to see
if they tasted of salt,
and they would receive a beating.
For us, it's like a borrowed memory
it's not my own memory,
it's my father's.
But it nests within you.
My sons definitely consider themselves Palestinians,
they grew up with it.
When they grew up and went to university,
what I really loved was how they would sit
and talk with their grandfather, my father.
All their questions,
they wouldn't ask me or their father,
they would ask their grandfather, because
he is the principal link with Palestine.
They would go over many of the stories,
many of the tales,
which created this link between the two generations.
You could hear them going deep into this memory
which is a part of the collective memory.
When my children started school,
I made a promise to myself
that they would remain in one place.
This being constantly on the move
makes one always feel like an alien,
a feeling that is carried on the inside
wherever you go
I don't believe that there is a place
where I have felt that I truly belong
that I'm a 100% from that place.
The place where I feel that, is in my imagination,
it's in my country Palestine.
But in reality, I never felt that sense of belonging,
that I am from a place,
that I am organically from there.
Lebanon is probably
the nearest thing to a homeland
but I always feel a sense of alienation.
As soon as I open my mouth
and start to speak
I immediately get the question:
- Would you like to go to Jaffa?
Me? I would love to.
I wish I could, I wish I could go to Jaffa.
You know how an orphan always
wants to meet their biological parents?
Even if they had abandoned him,
even if there were tragic conditions,
I feel like something of an orphan
I feel far from my roots and origins.
[ Remember when I was in Jaffa
Speak to us
ell us of Jaffa
My sail in the Port of Jaffa
O for the fishing days in Jaffa
I am from Fureidis,
In the District of Haifa
I am a resident of Mar Elias Camp.
My father's family left in 1948
and fled to Nabatiyyeh
then my mother and father got married
and went to live in Tal el-Zaatar Camp.
From Tal el-Zaatar
we came to Mar Elias Camp
and we are still here
in Mar Elias Camp.
We were still young, and my father
may God have mercy on his soul,
was killed in Tal el-Zaatar Camp
I mean he was never found,
we never knew whether he was dead or alive.
He's been missing since 1976.
My mother brought us up.
We are 8 girls and 2 boys,
in total 10 children. /\; -
My mother used to work
she was a cook in
one of the organizations
to be able to raise us.
It wasn't easy for her to raise us.
She also worked here,
in a school close to the Camp.
We also used to work cleaning houses.
When we first came out of Tal el-Zaatar
we went through hard times,
we went through difficult days.
My father was gone,
May God have mercy
on his soul, if he's dead.
Surely, he can't still be alive...
He must have grown old and
God has probably taken him back.
My mother used to tell us about
Palestine but not as much as she should have
because she worked,
and was both a father and a mother to us.
She had to raise a family of 10.
She told us only a few things
about Haifa,
about Fureidis
but only briefly,
not in any detail, not thoroughly.
When I first learned to embroider
I was around 13 or 14 years old.
About 28 or 29 years, a long time.
My sister-in-law taught me how to embroider
and I started doing it
and I'm still doing it regularly until now.
I could say embroidery now flows in my blood.
I cannot stop, I mean I cannot leave it.
There are 6 of us sisters who embroider
and my sister-in-law embroiders
so does my other sister-in-law
so do my nieces.
We get together with the neighbors,
and here we are, surviving.
We don't have a particular place we gather in.
In the summer we sit outdoors,
in the winter we go inside,
each one takes a corner,
she sits there and...
we all work on our embroidery.
In the past in Palestine,
women used to gather
in front of their houses
and also after leaving Palestine,
they would gather and embroider
they would put a basket with
all the balls of threads in the middle
and the women would sit ...
a word here and a word there
a stitch here, a stitch there,
and the time would pass.
While we're working on our embroidery,
we talk about all sorts of things.
I am very fast.
I work about 8 or 9 hours a day.
It depends on my circumstances
it depends on how much time I have,
the responsibilities of the house,
cooking, washing,
helping my children with their school work.
She gets up at 4am.
She performs ablutions, prays,
and then sits until 7:30am.
You know? I like solitude.
I like to sit by myself.
When I'm alone
I think of my children,
my thoughts drift to my children,
I think of myself,
my health, my well being.
I reflect on all sorts of things.
How to sort this or that out,
how to manage and get by.
By the grace of God
thoughts always drift and wander.
My head starts to spin with thoughts.
I like to embroider at night.
After I put the children to bed,
that's when I like to sit down and embroider
I stay until 11pm or midnight.
Sometimes, when there
are school holidays
I keep going until 1 or 2am,
I have no problem,
I keep working and I'm productive.
To tell you the truth, there are
two pieces that are dear to my heart.
The Beit Dajan piece that
took me two and a half months to finish.
I don't know how, but I felt that
I was in the heart of Palestine.
The Jerusalem piece in particular,
I finished it in 5 months and 17 days.
The Jerusalem piece...
How can I put it?
It gave me the incentive
to continue working on this project,
and to keep on embroidering
to ensure that embroidery will
never die out and disappear, never ever.
We will return one day to our neighborhood
and drown in...
I long to go there
I wish I could go there
visit Jerusalem
visit Fureidis
because people generally don't know Fureidis
they know Haifa,
not Fureidis the town, the village.
Oh heart how we have been displaced by the winds
Come, we will return
Come with me
My name is Amal ZIAD KAAWASH
I am a Palestinian born in Lebanon.
We are originally from Meiroun
a village in the North of Palestine,
in the district of Safad.
Meiroun is the village of the KAAWASH family.
What's particular about the village
is that only the KAAWASH family lived there.
It is a tiny village,
it is currently a religious Jewish Settlement.
Because all the inhabitants were from one family,
it is sometimes referred to as Meiroon KAAWASH.
Many members from the KAAWASH family
name their daughters Meiroun KAAWASH.
I do not have the Lebanese nationality,
neither do my mother and father.
Officially, I am still considered
a Palestinian refugee in Lebanon
and we carry the blue identity card which is
If we need to travel, we have a
special travel document for Palestinians
which Palestinians sometimes
call the 'coloring book'.
In this piece of embroidery, the part
that's meant to be the front-piece, the collar
the square-shaped collar
reminded me of a house.
It immediately reminded me of the
remains of the last house in Meiroun,
the house of the late Abu Talal KAAWASH.
Only one or two walls
of the house still stand
but it still gives the impression that
it is standing tall and watching people.
It's as if the openings or windows are eyes.
As if it can see the people looking
at its picture, those of us in the Diaspora
There is a character that I draw,
her name is Meiroun...
Meiroun is my daughter
who was born on paper.
She is a silhouette,
we do not see her face,
but we see that she is a girl, a silhouette.
She has two long braids
and she loves to play with
the moon, all the time.
When I called my blog Meiroun,
and when I named this girl Meiroun,
I wanted people who
had never heard of this tiny village
to get to know its name.
Now, almost eight years after
the birth of Meiroun the girl,
I am happy that very often
people mention Meiroun
without knowing its
connection with Amal KAAWASH.
It made me feel that
I had achieved something.
Perhaps the 'virtual liberation'
of the village of Meiroun.
Meiroun doesn't grow up.
She loves to play with balloons.
To her, the moon is like a balloon
she flies it high,
she plays with it,
she holds it by a string,
she flies it like a kite.
It is the same moon that looks out
over Meiroun the real village,
and Meiroun the girl who
lives all over the world
because she doesn't live in her homeland,
she lives in the Diaspora.
In addition to drawing,
I am also a singer an a composer.
I studied oriental singing for
four years at the Lebanese Conservatoire..
Ever( time I participate in
a Palestinian concert or event,
I find myself, as if by instinct,
either wearing a thobe on stage
or wearing some other item
of Palestinian embroidery.
One of the songs that I have written
Is a song about the Palestinian 'thobe'.
Though I have never performed it
I have a Palestinian thobe
Always hidden away in the wardrobe
\
I wore it once and sang
About people of Haifa and Birzeit
When back at home I packed it
Inside the wardrobe I hid it
I hid it and I wish that
It would return to its home
It will one day return to its home.
I really liked the embroidered
panel from Beer el-Sabih.
It embodies many stories, I
and many phases
it flows from
one phase to the other
and the last phase is joyful.
There is always full of hope.
It reminds me of a story
that had a major impact on my life..
After a long Diaspora,
and several moves from..
I was born In Jerusalem
we then lived
in Amman for a while,
then we moved to Beirut,
then I went to Tunis,
then I went to the US.
Finally, I returned to Ramallah.
However, throughout
my exile, I was always consoled
by the memory of a place,
my grandfather's house
which I will never forget.
The memory comes to me in
the form of an enormous door.
A door that I used to see as huge,
as if it were from the tale of Aladdin.
I would imagine it opening wide,
as if a treasure was waiting for me behind it
as if I was going to find someone special..
S0, when I first got married
and returned to Palestine,
I decided to go
to Jerusalem by myself.
I was going to face this memory
that had been haunting me all this time,
and I was going to prove to myself
that I belonged to this place
and that part of my memories
were connected to this place.
I eventually arrived
in the Old City of Jerusalem
to the Afghani corner,
right next to the Dome of the Rock.
I was very excited, believing that
I was going to find my life's dream.
I was going to confront it and see it.
I arrived and was shocked!
In place of an ancient
430-year-old wooden door,
I found a hideous iron door
painted all in green
a horrible color, that I couldn't believe
could have replaced the wooden door.
I knocked on the door hysterically.
A very handsome and graceful
young man opened the door.
When he first opened
the door with a smile on his face
I demanded “Where's the door?
Where's the original door of the house?"
He asked me “Who are you?”
And I replied
"I am the daughter of Ali and Fathiyeh
and this is my grandfather's house.
What are you doing here?
Where’s the door?
What you've done with it.
I demand to know
where you've put the door!”
He smiled gently and said to me
"Calm down, take it easy.
Please come inside and we'll talk.”
I went inside.
The courtyard was still the same
but they had transformed it into
a yard for remembrance gatherings (zikr).
I entered while he went
inside to make tea.
I started screaming
"You! You!
at are you doing here? Who are you?”
When he came back and
put the tea tray down on the table,
he looked at me and calmly said:
"I am your cousin.
I am Aouni, the son of your aunt Suheila.”
At that point I was stunned, I broke down.
He said "I will ask him if you could take the door
and I believe he will accept.”
The Sheikh did agree, and
the door is now in my house.
The door is here and
there are photos around it.
Those photos are the most
they are 'My Deceased'
to whom I am very attached.
There is a picture of my father, Ali TAHA
who became a martyr in 1972,
There is a picture of
Yasser Arafat, who raised me
and who also died in 2004.
Then there is a picture of my friend,
my lifelong friend, my husband's friend
my inspiration, and my mentor
from when I was a little girl
until he was taken from us
and passed away,
that is Mahmoud Darwish.
And there is a picture of the Iove
He too has become a picture...
The most important people
in my life have become pictures.
But I love them dearly
because they are not demanding.
Every day, I have my morning coffee
I do my reading,
all my life
takes place in front of this door
that was knocked on by all
the people I know and those I.don't. -
My grandfather, my grandmother,
my mother, my father,
my uncles, my cousins...
I look at this door and I imagine
all the fists that have knocked on it
or touched it, or closed it, or opened it
and I imagine beautiful tales.
So this door is a part of my life
and I think that, in addition
to many other things in my life,
it is the beautiful memory
that allows me to remain steadfast
and rooted in this place.
My name is Leila Atchan
I am a resident of Ramallah.
My family is originally from
a village called Al-Haditha
near Ledd and Jaffa.
The village has been destroyed.
As a child, I studied in Jerusalem
and continued my education in the USA
at two universities,
Harvard and Rutgers
I am a psychotherapist
with many years' experience working
with people suffering from trauma,
those who were traumatized
during the two Intifadas in Palestine,
Palestinian refugees in Denmark,
and with other groups
in Jordan, with Iraqis,
and now with Syrian and
Palestinian refugees from Syria.
As a child, I barely used to see,
some colors and large objects,
but nothing really significant.
I have seen colors before
that's why when you name a color
I am able to imagine it
to picture it in my mind
I have to say that it's only recently
that I began to appreciate embroidery.
Now I love it.
On my handbag, my scarf.
I also had a dress made with embroidery.
To me, embroidery
is about identity in the positive sense.
It represents Palestinian
identity as I would like it to be,
an artistic identity.
The concept of colors in the embroidery
IS a reflection of Palestinian identity as I like it,
an identity that has the capacity
to accommodate differences.
Which has been gradually diminishing.
That may be why I've started
to appreciate embroidery again.
At the core of Palestinian culture,
we did have diversity,.
Many things were accepted.
The other day, I was talking
to a 75-year-old woman
and she told me that the girls used to walk
around 20 km, from one village to another,
to attend;a.dance or a wedding.
Today, there are so many restrictions
and rules that are limiting.
It is as if the piece
of embroidery is vanishing.
But I always like to keep in mind
that the colors and diversity
in this piece represent pride.
A woman takes pride in I
her femininity, if 'the colors she chooses.
- This one here?
They are like a zig-zag...
made up of..
I imagine a woman with all her intricate
emotions, working on her embroidery piece.
She's probably thinking of a hundred things.
She may have moments of happiness,
she may have a secret love,
she may have times of sadness,
she may have all these things, > 4
but in spite of it all, she was
able to produce this piece.
- Muna, come on, give me the answer
I can feel how all of these
are connected to each other.
Here, there is something like a square,
connected to this thing next to it.
Different shapes
but all somehow connected to each other.
I think this is what makes
the entire piece beautiful.
Whether it's a square, or
whatever it is that you call these shapes.
-Io.me,
embroidery is linked to
women who are like my mother.
The mother who was able
to work in secret and support her family,
who was able to stand up to the soldiers
when they ha me to the house and beat up my father
she went.out proudly in her 'thobe?
and demanded that they release hims
She was not afraid.
This kind of woman, who is strong,
who can be feminine,
who can be a mother,
who can be a fighter, : -
who can be all those things
at a time when society is
trying to limit and constrain her.
Embroidery really
reminds me of her, the survivor.
reminds me of her, the surivor.
The woman who has been able to persist
- -and to do so artistically and with femininity.
My mother is still alive,
she is around 84 years old
and she-still wears the 'thobe'
%'
with a lot of pride.
When she goes out, particularly to
special occasion, she always wears a 'thobe'.
I am SUAD al-AMIRY,
the founder of the RIWAQ Center
\ for the protection of heritage in Palestine. '
I was born in Damascus,
because my mother is Damascene
and was raised in Amman.
I studied at
the American University of Beirut.
I spent my youth between
Jordan, Damascus and Beirut.
I returned to Palestine
to teach at Birzeit University
and since then
I have lived in Ramallah.
In truth, I returned to Palestine
because a part of me
has always searched for Palestine
but the main reason for my return
was my interest 2
in Palestinian architecture
in 'architecture without
an architect' as it's called.
I went to Palestine on a visit,
to study Palestinian architecture
that was in 1981.
I thou ht.I would be there
I fell in love with Palestine,
and I fell in love with a man in Palestine,
and as a result I decided to take up
a teaching post at Birzeit University.
From 1981 until now,
the six months have become almost 33 years.
No one in my family embroidered.
But that's not all,
when I became aware of embroidery
I became aware of class consciousness
of class differences
when it comes to embroidery.
I remember when a man
came to ask for my sister's hand
the. room's mother wore a "'thobe"
It made me want
to understand why my mother cried
if the woman was wearing a "'thobe"?!
Later on I understood that it was about
the distinction between urbanites and peasants.
This piece...now I really have to
rid myself of my mother's prejudices
and my first impressions.
To me, it signifies something beautiful.
Aesthetically, as an architect
or someone interested in art
or someone who is highly visual,
first of all, it is a beautiful
piece of art with.regards to.the colors,
It could possibly be
an early form of abstract art
one speaks of artists
such as Mondrian or others.
If one doesn't know the
political background of the piece, '
it could be by Miro
or any other modern artist.
There is a recurring story
the story of the 420 villages
that were bulldozed by Israel.
They obliterated them.
So, when I returned to Palestine, I
I began to research Palestinian architecture ,1
I found that the villages that currently
exist in the West Bank and Gaza are actually 420!
That's how the number 420
became a magical number for me.
The Israelis destroyed 420 villages
and we must protect
the remaining 420 villages
I have always felt that
the struggle between us and Israel
is over the identity of the place.
There were many things the Palestinians
were unable to carry with them to the Diaspora
they were able to carry
a diploma if they were educated
they were able to carry a song to sing.
"-* - - > —— Or the Palestinian accent
which I:still preserve 65 years later.
I think embroidery is one of those things
that they were able to carry as a profession.
Sometimes | feel that
embroidery is like a grandmother’s tale
like a bed-time story,
where children ask their mothers
"Please sing me Teta's tale".
It's always the women who carry
heritage and culture
to youngsters through storytelling.
I feel that embroidery embodies that.
It's like an oral story
especially that every place has its own narrative.
The embroidery of Ramallah
is different from that of Asdoud,
the combination of white
and blue implies one thing
the symbolism represents
fertility and bounty...
I often feel it is similar
to the tale of 'Little Red Riding Hood'
where each generation retells the story..
Buildings are not transportable
they are fixed in space
but embroidery is migratory it's like a refugee.
There is the notion of
'refugeehood' attached to it
and there is also a sense of continuity.
Where did I grow up? In Jerusalem.
I'm a resolute Jerusalemite.
I lived my entire life in Jerusalem
until I was 19 and a half
when I met a man and we got
married and moved to Martinique.
We lived for five years on
the island of Martinique in the Caribbean.
When I see this piece, I immediately
think of the tiles in my father's house.
The tiles of my father's house in Baq'a
which appear to almost be embroidered,
embroidered with a paintbrush
instead of a needle-.
On Fridays when I have my day-off from work,
I take walks around Baq'a.
Nowadays, Baq'a has become
an all Jewish neighborhood.
So, one day I stood
in front of my father's house
and the idea of standing in front of the house
was very provocative to the people
who are now living in my father's house.
They bought the house
from the Israeli government.
At the time, in 1998,
Netanyahu was Prime Minister
the Israeli government wanted
to expropriate everything that existed,
especially the most precious things
there are in Palestine, on its land
other than its people -
but they don't consider us humans nor want us around -
are the Arab houses
with their beautiful architecture
and which they can sell off for millions.
I never had the chance to live in the house
which is why I sometimes feel that..
...that it's in my blood
When she asked me,
the Israeli settler woman
"I have the key , how can you prove that
this is your father's house?".
I do have the documents,
the deeds are with me at home
but I don't carry them around with me!
I also worry about them.
I need to keep them safe.
Like the tiles or the pieces of embroidery
or the embroidered thobe,
I hold on to the deeds that prove
that this is my father's house.
So I said to her: “Right here,
if you open it up, if you cut open my veins
you will know that it's my father's house".
So, every time I go to my father's house,
they call the police
and I get handcuffed
and I get threatened with expulsion...
But, if I were to tell you about
what there is inside my father's house,
which I was only able to enter once
when they were renovating the house...
I was able to go in
because the doors were open
and the workmen renovating Arab houses,
like those who build
the apartheid wall and the settlements,
are unfortunately Palestinian laborers.
The man who was removing the tiles,
was an Arab, a Palestinian.
I found him removing the tiles
and I asked him "What are you doing?
Why are you removing these beautiful tiles?”
The most beautiful thing
in these old houses are the tiles.
Nowadays, there is no one who
can make these beautiful designs.
He answered me,
"Well this is what they want
the Jewish settlers want me
to take out all the tiles
and rearrange them in
a different pattern and design”.
I stood there observing him
and found him taking 10 at a time
stacking them together in a wooden box
like files, like an archive.
Like so...
One after the other.
Then he took them to
a corner behind the house.
50, I grabbed an entire box
and put it in my car.
Then I took another one,
each had 10 tiles,
and we made a stunning 'carpet' with them.
This tile carpet,reminds me of embroidery.
The geometric pattern,
the colors of sand,
of the sun,
it's very beautiful..
I feel like I have...
How can I put it?
Not that I have revived our heritage,
we seem to think that
we actually revive heritage,
but that I may have
documented my own story.
My story , Huda's and
the story of my father, Farid
who built a house and was deprived of it.
Now the tiles are an integral part of my life.
Dina Nasser,
I was born in Jerusalem.
I spent my youth in Jerusalem.
I studied in England
and returned to Jerusalem,
and now I work in Jerusalem.
I am a Registered Nurse
and I also work as a health advisor.
This piece of embroidery reminds me
She always gave me gifts of
embroidery on birthday stand on my wedding.
When she gave.meithis‘piece
I put it up in our house in Jerusalem
when we were newlyweds.
Then we lived in Birzeit for a few years,
and I hung it in our house in Birzeit. "
Then we returned to Jerusalem
without the embroidery
and also without my husband.
Because of the Zionist occupation
I have to preserve my existence
and presence In Jerusalem
because I cannot
live outside of Jerusalem.
Yet we cannot live
with Youssef in Birzeit.
If we were to live with him
I would lose my Jerusalem ID
and that of my three children.
And Youssef is not allowed
to come live with us in Jerusalem.
He hasn't been granted
the 'Family Reunification' papers.
He was born in Birzeit,
but his parents emigrated
so he returned
to Palestine as an American
him 'Family Reuni nation'.
Even after we were married,
we tried four times.
But until now he has not been granted it.
This year it will be our
30th wedding anniversary,
the past six, seven years
have been the toughest years.
Because now we only
see each other on special occasions.
Even on special occasions,
he cannot come here,
even for weddings or funerals,
but we visit him on special
occasions and over weekends.
However, if we spend
too many days away
they'd consider our main residence
to be outside of Jerusalem
and the Israelis can come
and take away my Jerusalem ID
if they can prove that.
Our main residence is.outside Jerusalem.
So we go to see him like visitors
and when we leave,
it's as if we’ve committed a crime
We obliterate all traces
of our presence there.
This is part of the Israeli policy
for the ethnic cleansing of Jerusalem.
So, if we decide to live
with Youssef as a family
then with one stroke of the en
And that way they would have
easily gotten rid of four people.
But it doesn't end here,
it's continuous hardship.
If the children
travel to study abroad,
they need to prove their
existence all over again
when they return to Jerusalem.
If they are studying abroad,
they are considered non-residents.
If for any reason .
they stay on after their studies
they are considered
as having left Jerusalem for good.
I have accepted this,
but I hope that I will not regret
having subjected my children to this life.
Our children never had
the chance to have a stable family life.
There have been many family occasions
when each of us was in a different corner
even funerals,
like when my father passed away
the Israelis didn't think it was sufficient justification
to give him an entry permit so that he can be with us,
or when my daughter
fell and ended up in hospital,
he wasn’t allowed to be with us.
In Jerusalem, we are reminded
of the occupation on a daily basis
because the repression is
continuous on a daily basis.
There is a settlement close to us
right next door.
When the clashes started,
they put up a barbed fence
between us and them.
There is also a checkpoint
right next to the house.
And they decide to close the checkpoint,
we are obliged to take a long
detour as if we are going to the West Bank
we have to circle the roundabout
so that we can get back
to Jerusalem and cross the checkpoint.
So yes,
when you live in Jerusalem
You are faced with the.
ccupation on a daily basis.
I cannot live
outside Jerusalem.
I work at the Muttale' Hospital,
when 1 go down the hill.
and see Jerusalem
I stop the car.
Every single day, as I return home,
I slow the car down
and I look out at Jerusalem,
I take a deep breath
and I say to myself,
“This is why I am here”.
It's a continuous struggle
to validate our existence in Jerusalem.
When my son Fares was born,
I was unable .
to register him for six years,
at the time, his father
had taken the West Bank ID
and now was required
to have 'Family Reunification'.
They had taken away
my ID and those of the kids.
So one day, I decided
to call the Jerusalem Municipality
to check where they had registered me.
When I called, a woman answered
she said to me “Sorry, you do not exist”
I gave her my details
and my ID number
I remember that .
that was 20 years ago, I cried.
I said to myself “All this time
and now a I of a sudden I do not exist!”
Just because someone decided
to simply strike me off?!
Is it that simple
that “I don't exist”??
I thought to myself, I should let
my son Fares loose in the Ministry of Interior,
a six-year-old boy,
to show you that he exists,
that I exist
that my children exist.
That we all exist.
That robe now finds its proper place
in the thread of the story.
It has long ceased to be nearly a dress.
Beauty is no longer its sole attribute,
even though beauty remains
one of its most resplendent features.
The surface of the robe
Is now the story-teller.
Sometimes it is the homeland,
and at others it is, of course, a profession.
It is a memory,
a heritage,
a weight of history,
a sense of duty.
There is pride In it
but also weariness,
and both meet in it.
Each woman sits and tells her story.
She speaks of her present
with fervor, lucidity and passionate love.
With every stitch
the woman is hiding a story,
a thought,
a sigh.
The individual threads
do not melt in some collective narrative
even though they embroider that narrative.
Twelve women,
twelve life-spans
and stories from Palestine,
a land whose position was fixed
on the map o the world
but is now embroidered on its face.